If you know the Lagrangian of a system, the
Euler-Lagrange equations will provide you
with the equations of motion and describe
how the system will evolve over time.
Before we start, we need to talk about two
things. First, we define the so-called action
of a system as the integral over the Lagrangian.
For classical mechanics, this means the time
integral over the Lagrangian function, however
for relativistic mechanics, the Lorentz-covariant
formulation involves the spacetime integral
over the Lagrangian density. This action is
a functional, this means it takes a function
(in this case the Lagrangian) as an input
and after some calculation, the result is
a number. So every configuration of the system
yields as the corresponding action just a
different number. This brings us to the second
point: Hamilton’s principle. Hamilton’s
principle states, that the system we are considering
evolves in such a way, that the action takes
on an extremal value. In other words, if we
slightly change the path that the system takes,
the change in action will be almost zero.
A small mathematical detail here is, that
we do not change the starting and end points
of the path, which means that delta q for
some starting time t_1 and end time t_2 is
zero. Similar arguments lead to corresponding
constraints in the relativistic case, where
we do not change the fields at the beginning
and end point, just somewhere along the way.
Now we can start deriving the Euler-Lagrange
equations. We start by explicitly calculating
the change in the action, knowing that whatever
comes out in the end must be zero according
to Hamilton’s principle. For the classical
version, this means varying the Lagrangian
with respect to q and multiplying a small
change in q as well as varying in q dot and
multiplying a small change in q dot. For the
relativistic version, we do this with respect
to the fields phi and their derivatives d_mu
phi.
A change in the time derivative of q is the
same as the time derivative of the change
in q, so let’s write it like this. Similarly,
we can exchange the delta and the derivative
on the right.
Next we use the inverse product rule, which
let’s us write a function and the derivative
of another function as the derivative of their
product minus the derivative of the first
function times the second function. We now
write the second term as the time derivative
of dL over dq dot and delta q minus the time
derivative of dL over dq dot times delta q.
On the right, this is the same, but with a
d_mu.
From here on we can evaluate parts of the
integral, in particular the total derivative
which is now evaluated between the end time
and the starting time. As for the other terms,
we can factor out the delta q. On the right,
we evaluate between x^mu_2 and x^mu_1 and
also pull out the delta phi.
Due to our assumptions, the first term vanishes,
since it is exactly the change of q or phi
evaluated at the boundary points. That’s
why this term is usually called a „boundary
term“. And remember, since we started from
a small change in the action, the terms in
brackets have to vanish due to Hamilton’s
principle. And this is what leads to the Euler-Lagrange
equations.
Remember, that q here stands for all the variables
you have in your system. So if there is, for
example, an x and a y, you actually have two
Euler-Lagrange equations, one for x and x
dot and the other for y and y dot. As you
can see, instead of two first-order differential
equations in the Hamiltonian formulation,
we now have one second order differential
equation in the Lagrangian formulation for
each variable. And that’s pretty much it
for now, thanks for watching.